tutanota.com 2019-12-15

# Tutanota Privacy Statement

### Privacy Statement of Tutao GmbH

_This Data Privacy Statement is provided in English for your convenience. Please note that in case of a dispute or discrepancy between the German Data Privacy Statement and the English translation, theGerman version shall prevail._

**Status: May 25, 2018**

#### General

We are responsible for the protection of your personal data, and we take this responsibility very seriously. Therefore

  * Tutanota is based on the data privacy principles "data minimization" and "privacy by design",
  * all user data is stored end-to-end encrypted in Tutanota (except for email addresses of users as well as senders and recipients of emails),
  * we have technical and organizational measures in place which protect your data best possible,
  * all data is stored in ISO 27001 certified data centers in Germany.

Processing of personal data takes place in compliance with the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) as well as with the local data protection laws applicable to the Tutao GmbH.

We are always at your disposal for any questions about privacy. Please contact us via email: hello@tutao.de.

#### Name and Address of the controller

Tutao GmbH  
Hanomaghof 2  
30449 Hannover  
Germany

Email address: hello@tutao.de

#### Personal data

All personal data is kept secure by us and thus protected from unauthorized access.

For the initiation of a contractual relationship and for service provision we collect

  * the newly registered email address

as inventory data.

For invoicing and determining the VAT we collect for paid product variants

  * the domicile of the customer (country)
  * the invoicing address (for private users optional)
  * the VAT identification number (only for business customers of some countries)

as inventory data.

For the transaction of payments we collect depending on the chosen payment method the following payment data (inventory data):

  * Banking details (account number and sort code and IBAN/BIC, if necessary bank name, account holder),
  * credit card data,
  * PayPal user name.

This inventory data is processed for the performance of the contract with the customer according to Art. 6 GDPR 1. b). For the execution of direct debiting we will share your banking details with the authorized credit institution. For the execution of PayPal payments we will share your PayPal data with PayPal (Europe).

  * Address: PayPal (Europe) S.à r.l. et Cie, S.C.A.,22-24 Boulevard Royal, L-2449 Luxembourg

For the execution of credit card payments your credit card data will be shared with our payment service provider [Braintree](https://www.braintreepayments.com/). This includes the transfer of personal data into a third country (USA). [An agreement entered into with Braintree](https://www.braintreepayments.com/assets/Braintree-PSA-Model-Clauses-March2018.pdf) defines appropriate safeguards and demands that the data is only processed in compliance with the GDPR and only for the purpose of execution of payments.

Tutanota provides services for saving, editing, presentation and electronic transmission of data, such as email service, contact management and data storage. This content data is voluntarily entered into Tutanota by the customer. When signing up for a Tutanota account, you give consent to the processing of this data according to Art. 6 DSGVO 1. a). All textual content is encrypted for the user and its communication partners in a way that even Tutao GmbH has no access to the data. This data can be deleted by the user.

In order to maintain email server operations, for error diagnosis and for prevention of abuse, mail server logs are stored max. 7 days. These logs contain sender and recipient email addresses and time of connection but no customer IP addresses. Storage takes place for the purposes of the legitimate interests pursued by the controller according to Art. 6 DSGVO 1. f).

In order to maintain operations, for prevention of abuse and and for visitors analysis, IP addresses of users are processed. Storage only takes place for IP addresses made anonymous which are therefore not personal data any more. This processing takes place for the purposes of the legitimate interests pursued by the controller according to Art. 6 DSGVO 1. f).

With the exception of payment data, we will not disclose your personal data including your email address to third parties. However, we can be legally bound to provide content data (in case of a valid German court order) and inventory data to prosecution services. There will be no sale of data.

#### Period of data storage

The personal data shall be deleted no later than 30 days after termination of the contract, unless specific reasons to the contrary apply in an individual case. In case a customer objected to the amount of the charged fees, the accounting data may be stored until the objections are terminally clarified. Furthermore, inventory data can be stored for up to two years if the handling of a complaint and other reasons require this for an orderly settlement of the contract. Moreover the deletion of inventory and billing data may be omitted provided that legal regulations or the prosecution of claims require this. Order-related data and the addresses associated with the order are stored in respect to tax, contract and commercial law retention periods and erased at the end of those periods.

#### Rights of the data subject

Insofar that you have given us your consent to process your personal data, we would like to point out that you can withdraw your consent for the future at any time. Upon request we will inform you about the data we have stored about you free of charge. Please send a message with your request to hello@tutao.de. In addition we are obliged to delete, to correct or to restrict processing of the data stored about you upon request. Additionally, you may **object to the processing of your personal data** as well as to lodge a complaint with a supervisory authority and the federal commissioner for data privacy of Germany (Husarenstr. 30, 53117 Bonn). You can make use of your right to data portability by exporting your personal data stored with us in Tutanota.

#### Cookies

We do not use cookies.

#### Contact from web page

On our web pages we offer the opportunity to get in contact with us via email or contact form. In doing so personal data is voluntarily transferred to us, stored automatically and only used for the purpose of dealing with the request and getting in contact with the affected person. We will not disclose this personal data to third parties.
